Ten years ago, on a Tuesday morning,
منذ عشر سنوات في صباح ذات ثلاثاء
I conducted a parachute jump at Fort Bragg, North Carolina.
قمت بالقفز المظلي في شمال كاليفورنيا في منطقة فورت براج
It was a routine training jump, like many more I'd done
كانت قفزة تدريبية .. كالعديد من القفزات التي اقوم بها
since I became a paratrooper
منذ ان غدوت مظلياً
27 years before.
منذ 27 عاماً
We went down to the airfield early
لقد ذهبنا الى الحقل الجوي مبكرين
because this is the Army and you always go early.
لانه في الجيش عليك ان تكون دوماً مبكراً
You do some routine refresher training,
تقوم ببعض تمارين الاحماء
and then you go to put on your parachute and a buddy helps you.
ومن ثم ترتدي مظلتك بمساعدة صديقك
And you put on the T-10 parachute.
ترتدي مظلة ( تي 10 )
And you're very careful how you put the straps,
وتراعي تماما اماكن الاربطة
particularly the leg straps because they go between your legs.
خاصة تلك التي تمر بين ساقيك
And then you put on your reserve, and then you put on your heavy rucksack.
ومن ثم ترفع المظلة الى الظهر وتصبح كحقيبة ظهر ثقيلة
And then a jumpmaster comes,
ومن ثم يأتي مسؤول القفز
and he's an experienced NCO in parachute operations.
وهو ضابط صف متمرس في عمليات الجوقلة ( القفز المظلي )
He checks you out, he grabs your adjusting straps
يتأكد من عدتك .. ويشد الاربطة
and he tightens everything
ويتأكد من متانتها
so that your chest is crushed,
ويشدها بحيث يضغط على صدرك بشدة
your shoulders are crushed down,
وعلى اكتافك ايضاً
and, of course, he's tightened so your voice goes up a couple octaves as well.
واحيانا يستمر بالشد حتى تصدر انت صوتاً متألماً تبعا له
Then you sit down, and you wait a little while,
ومن ثم تجلس .. وتنتظر قليلاً
because this is the Army.
وهكذا دوما في الجيش
Then you load the aircraft, and then you stand up and you get on,
ومن ثم يحين موعد الصعود على ظهر الطائرة .. وتقف ... وتترجل
and you kind of lumber to the aircraft like this, in a line of people,
لتسير في الصف من اجل الدخول الى الطائرة
and you sit down on canvas seats on either side of the aircraft.
حتى تصل الى مكانك وتجلس على مقاعد متقابلة
And you wait a little bit longer,
وتنتظر مرة أخرى
because this is the Air Force teaching the Army how to wait.
لان القوة الجوية تعلم الجنود الانتظار
Then you take off.
ومن ثم تقلع الطائرة
And it's painful enough now --
والجلوس مؤلم حقاً
and I think it's designed this way --
اعتقد انه صمم لهذه الغاية
it's painful enough so you want to jump.
لكي يتولد في نفسك رغبة في القفز
You didn't really want to jump, but you want out.
انت لا تريد ان تقفز .. ولكنك تريد ذلك .. بسبب الجلوس هناك
So you get in the aircraft, you're flying along,
حسناً انت في الطائرة . واثناء الرحلة
and at 20 minutes out, these jumpmasters start giving you commands.
يقوم مسؤول القفز باعطاء التعليمات . مثل - باقي 20 دقيقة -
They give 20 minutes -- that's a time warning.
باقي عشرين دقيقة للقفز - هذا للتنويه -
You sit there, OK.
تخيل انك جالسٌ هناك ..
Then they give you 10 minutes.
ومن ثم باقي 10 دقائق
And of course, you're responding with all of these.
حتماً انت تتجاوب مع كل هذا
And that's to boost everybody's confidence, to show that you're not scared.
وهذا التنويه يدفع بثقة الجميع .. خاصة ان لا احد يريد ان يبدو خائفاً
Then they give you, "Get ready."
ثم يقال " إستعد "
Then they go, "Outboard personnel, stand up."
ثم يقال " القوات المجوقلة .. قف "
If you're an outboard personnel, now you stand up.
ان كنت من القوات المجوقلة سوف تقف اولا
If you're an inboard personnel, stand up.
ومن ثم يقف من سيبقى في الطائرة
And then you hook up, and you hook up your static line.
ومن ثم يتم ربطك بخطاف الى حبل في اعلى الطائرة
And at that point, you think, "Hey, guess what?
في هذا الحين تقول في نفسك ..
I'm probably going to jump.
يبدو انني سوف اقفز لا محالة
There's no way to get out of this at this point."
لانه بعد هذه الخطوة لا يوجد مجال للتراجع
You go through some additional checks, and then they open the door.
يتم اجراء بعض الاختبارات على المعدات .. ومن ثم يفتح الباب
And this was that Tuesday morning in September,
وكان حينها صباح يوم ثلاثاء في شهر سبتمبر
and it was pretty nice outside.
وكانت الاجواء رائعة في الخارج
So nice air comes flowing in.
وكان العواء العليل يتدفق في الاجواء
The jumpmasters start to check the door.
ومن ثم بدأ مسؤول القفز بالتحقق من باب الطائرة
And then when it's time to go,
ومن ثم حان وقت القفز
a green light goes and the jumpmaster goes, "Go."
حيث يظهر ضوء اخضر .. ويقول مسؤول القفز " إنطلقوا "
The first guy goes, and you're just in line,
يقفز الرجل الاول .. وانت تقف في الصف
and you just kind of lumber to the door.
وتقترب من الباب
Jump is a misnomer; you fall.
في الحقيقة هي ليست قفز .. انها وقوع
You fall outside the door,
انت تقع الى خارج الطائرة
you're caught in the slipstream.
ويتحكم بك تيار الهواء
The first thing you do is lock into a tight body position --
او شيء يجب القيام به هو تثبيت جسدك بوضع محدد
head down in your chest, your arms extended,
راسك منخفض نحو صدرك . وايديك منبسطتين
put over your reserve parachute.
مرتفعتان الى اعلى المظلة
You do that because, 27 years before,
وانا اقوم بهذا لانه منذ 27 عاماً
an airborne sergeant had taught me to do that.
علمني ضابط قوات مجوقلة ان اقوم بذلك
I have no idea whether it makes any difference,
ولا اعلم ان قمت بغير هذا هل سيختلف الامر
but he seemed to make sense,
ولكن يبدو القيام بذلك منطقياً
and I wasn't going to test the hypothesis that he'd be wrong.
ولست بصدد اختبار اي شيء آخر لكي أثبت انهم مخطئون
And then you wait for the opening shock
ومن ثم انت تقع حتى يحين موعد صدمة فتح المظلة
for your parachute to open.
حين تقوم بسحب المظلة
If you don't get an opening shock, you don't get a parachute --
وان لم تمر بصدمة فتح المظلة .. لن تفتح المظلة
you've got a whole new problem set.
وهنا ستواجهك مشكلة اخرى
But typically you do; typically it opens.
ولكن في الواقع هي تفتح .. دوما تفتح
And of course, if your leg straps aren't set right,
وحتماً ان لم تكن اربطة الساقين في مكانها الصحيح
at that point you get another little thrill.
فسوف تشعر بألم شديد ..
Boom.
"بووووم"
So then you look around,
ومن ثم تنظر من حولك
you're under a canopy and you say, "This is good."
وترى موقع الهبوط في الاكاديمة اسفل منك " هذا جيد "
Now you prepare for the inevitable.
والان انت تستعد للأصعب
You are going to hit the ground.
انت على وشك الارتطام بالارض
You can't delay that much.
ولايمكنك تاخير هذا كثيرا
And you really can't decide where you hit very much,
ولايمكنك ان تقرر المكان الذي سوف تهبط فيه
because they pretend you can steer,
انهم يوهموك انهم يستطيعون التحكم
but you're being delivered.
ولكن لا .. الرياح تتحكم بكل شيء
So you look around, where you're going to land,
حسناً .. تنظر من حولك .. والى اين ستهبط
you try to make yourself ready.
وتحاول ان تهيء نفسك
And then as you get close, you lower your rucksack below you on a lowering line,
وما ان تقترب .. تقوم تخفيض حقيبتك الى ادنى من خط العلام الموجود
so that it's not on you when you land,
لكي لا تصبح فوقك اثناء الهبوط
and you prepare to do a parachute-landing fall.
وعندما تستعد لفتح المظلة
Now the Army teaches you
فان الجيش يعلمك
to do five points of performance --
بان تقوم بخمس تعليمات تخص ضبط
the toes of your feet,
اصابع القدمين
your calves, your thighs,
الوركين .. الفخذين
your buttocks and your push-up muscles.
الارداف .. وعضلات البطن
It's this elegant little land, twist and roll.
لانها محورية من اجل امتصاص الصدمة والتدحرج حين الهبوط
And that's not going to hurt.
وهذا امرٌ غير مؤذي
In 30-some years of jumping, I never did one.
لقد قفزت بالمظلات طيلة 30 عام .. ولم اتبع التعليمات الخمس على الاطلاق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I always landed like a watermelon out of a third floor window.
كنت دائما اهبط كما تهبط " البطيخة " من الدور الـثالث
And as soon as I hit,
وما ان ارتطم
the first thing I did is I'd see if I'd broken anything that I needed.
اول شيء اقوم به .. هو التحقق من الكسور
I'd shake my head,
فأهز رأسي
and I'd ask myself the eternal question:
واسئل نفسي بعض الاسئلة
"Why didn't I go into banking?"
" اين اضع اموالي ؟ "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'd look around,
ومن ثم انظر من حولي
and then I'd see another paratrooper,
وارى مظلي آخر
a young guy or girl,
فتاة شابة .. او فتى
and they'd have pulled out their M4 carbine
وقد اخرجوا بندقيتهم الرشاشة
and they'd be picking up their equipment.
وبدأوا بحمل امتعتهم
They'd be doing everything
وهم يقومون بكل شيء
that we had taught them.
قمنا بتعليمهم اياه
And I realized
وأدركت
that, if they had to go into combat,
انه ان ذهبنا الى معركة
they would do what we had taught them and they would follow leaders.
سوف ينفذون الامور التي تعلموها . وسوف يتبعون القادة
And I realized that, if they came out of combat,
وادرك انه ان نجى هؤلاء من المعركة
it would be because we led them well.
فان ذلك لاننا استطعنا قيادتهم بصورة صحيحة
And I was hooked again on the importance of what I did.
وهنا ادركت اهمية ما اقوم به
So now I do that Tuesday morning jump,
لنعد الى قفزة يوم الثلاثاء
but it's not any jump --
انها ليست قفزة اعتيادية
that was September 11th, 2001.
كانت في 11 من سبتمبر من عام 2001
And when we took off from the airfield, America was at peace.
وعندما اقلعنا من المطار كان لم يشوب أمريكا شيئاً بعد
When we landed on the drop-zone, everything had changed.
وعندما هبطنا الى المهبط .. كان كل شيء تغير
And what we thought
ان ما نعيه
about the possibility of those young soldiers going into combat
عن امكانية دخول هؤلاء الجنود الى ارض المعركة
as being theoretical
كان نظري
was now very, very real --
ولكنه الآن .. واقعي .. واقعي جداً
and leadership seemed important.
وبدأت القيادة الان محورية
But things had changed;
فالامور تغيرت ..
I was a 46-year-old brigadier general.
لقد كنت برتبة عميد .. وكنت ابلغ من العمر 46 عاماً
I'd been successful,
وكنت ناجحاً الى ذلك الوقت
but things changed so much
لكن الامور تغيرت كثيراً
that I was going to have to make some significant changes,
مما استوجب مني تغيرات كثيرة ايضاً
and on that morning, I didn't know it.
ولم اكن اعيها في ذلك الصباح
I was raised with traditional stories of leadership:
فانا قد تربيت على اساليب القيادة التقليدية
Robert E. Lee, John Buford at Gettysburg.
اسلوب روبرت لي جون بوفرد في جيتيسبرغ
And I also was raised
ونشأت على
with personal examples of leadership.
نماذج قيادية شخصية
This was my father in Vietnam.
مثل والدي الذي كان في فيتنام
And I was raised to believe
وقد تربيت على ان أؤمن
that soldiers were strong and wise
ان الجنود يجب ان يكونوا اقوياء واذكياء
and brave and faithful;
وشجعان ومخلصين
they didn't lie, cheat, steal
ولا يسرقون ولا يغشون ولا يكذبون
or abandon their comrades.
او يتخلوا ان رفاقهم
And I still believe real leaders are like that.
وما زلت اؤمن ان الجنود الحقيقيون هم كذلك
But in my first 25 years of career,
ولكن في السنوات الـ 25 من مسيرتي المهنية
I had a bunch of different experiences.
تعلمت الكثير من الخبرات
One of my first battalion commanders,
ان قائد كتيبتي الاولى
I worked in his battalion for 18 months
بقيت تحت امرته 18 شهراً
and the only conversation he ever had with Lt. McChrystal
والحديث الوحيد الذي تم بيني وبينه - الملازم ماك كريستال -
was at mile 18 of a 25-mile road march,
كان على الطريق 18 اثناء مسيرة 25 ميل
and he chewed my ass for about 40 seconds.
كان قد تسلط علي لمدة 40 ثانية
And I'm not sure that was real interaction.
ولست متاكداً ان كان حديث مباشر بينا قد جرى
But then a couple of years later, when I was a company commander,
ولكن بعد بضع سنوات .. غدوت مساعد قائد
I went out to the National Training Center.
وانتقلت الى مركز التدريب القومي
And we did an operation,
وكنا نقوم بعملية تدريبية
and my company did a dawn attack --
حيث كان شريكي في القيادة ينفذ عملية هجوم في الفجر
you know, the classic dawn attack:
اعني هجوم في الفجر حقاً
you prepare all night, move to the line of departure.
تستعد في الليل .. ومن ثم تقترب من خط المواجهة
And I had an armored organization at that point.
وكان لدي هناك فرقة مسلحة
We move forward, and we get wiped out --
وتقدمنا لكي نصد الهجوم .. وتم سحقنا حينها
I mean, wiped out immediately.
اعني .. سحقنا تماماً في ذلك التدريب
The enemy didn't break a sweat doing it.
ولم يبذل الطرف الآخر اي مجهود لذلك
And after the battle,
وبعد المعركة التدريبية
they bring this mobile theater and they do what they call an "after action review"
يجتمع الجميع .. ونعرض ماحدث على شاشة عرض كبيرة
to teach you what you've done wrong.
ونقوم بتعليم الجنود وتنبيههم عن مواقع الاخطاء
Sort of leadership by humiliation.
انه نوعاً من تسلط القاعدة على المرؤوسين
They put a big screen up, and they take you through everything:
حيث يعرض كل شي على الشاشة الكبيرة .. ويفصل الحدث جزءا بجزء
"and then you didn't do this, and you didn't do this, etc."
ويبدا القادة " لا يمكنك القيام بهذا .. .هذا تصرف خاطىء .. على هذا النحو "
I walked out feeling as low
لقد خرجت حينها محبطاً
as a snake's belly in a wagon rut.
كانت نفسيتي متدنية جداً بعد تلك الهزيمة
And I saw my battalion commander, because I had let him down.
ومن ثم مررت بالعميد ذاته .. كنت قد خيبت ظنه
And I went up to apologize to him,
فقررت الاعتذار منه
and he said, "Stanley, I thought you did great."
فقال لي " ستانلي .. اعتقد انك قمت بعمل رائع .. "
And in one sentence,
وفي جملة واحدة
he lifted me, put me back on my feet,
ارتفعت معنوياتي عالياً ..
and taught me that leaders can let you fail
وهذا علمني .. ان القادة يمكنهم ان يسمحوا لك بان تُخطىء - تفشل
and yet not let you be a failure.
ولكن لن يسمحون لك بان تغدو منهزماً
When 9/11 came,
وعندما جاء 11/9
46-year-old Brig. Gen. McChrystal sees a whole new world.
كنت قد اصبحت جنرالاً و كان العالم قد تغير بصورة تامة
First, the things that are obvious, that you're familiar with:
بداية هناك تغيرات واضحة .. الجميع يعرفها
the environment changed --
فقد تغيرت البيئة
the speed, the scrutiny,
والسرعة .. والدقة
the sensitivity of everything now is so fast,
وحساسية الادوات
sometimes it evolves faster
واحيانا يكون التطوير سريعاً
than people have time to really reflect on it.
بحيث لا يستوعب الاشخاص هذا التطوير التكنولوجي
But everything we do
وغدونا نقوم بكل شيء
is in a different context.
بصورة مختلفة
More importantly, the force that I led
والاكثر اهمية .. هو ان القوة التي كنت اقودها
was spread over more than 20 countries.
كانت منتشرة على نطاق 20 دولة
And instead of being able to get all the key leaders
وبدلاً من ان اكون قادراً على ان اجمع القادة خاصتي في
for a decision together in a single room
غرفة واحدة لنخرج بقرار حاسم
and look them in the eye and build their confidence
وان استطيع من التواصل فيما بيننا بصورة مباشرة و بناءة للثقة
and get trust from them,
على نحو متبادل
I'm now leading a force that's dispersed,
فانا اليوم اقود هذه القوات المبعثرة
and I've got to use other techniques.
عن طريق تقنيات مختلفة
I've got to use video teleconferences, I've got to use chat,
فانا استخدم المؤتمرات المرئية .. والمحادثة عبر الانترنت
I've got to use email, I've got to use phone calls --
والايميل .. والهاتف
I've got to use everything I can,
كان يتوجب علي ان استخدم كل ما يتوفر لدي
not just for communication,
ليس فحسب للتواصل
but for leadership.
بل للقيادة
A 22-year-old individual
كان هناك فرد في الـ 22 من عمره
operating alone,
يقود بمفرده
thousands of miles from me,
على بعد آلاف الاميال من مركزي
has got to communicate to me with confidence.
وكان يجب ان اتواصل معه .. وان يكون هناك
I have to have trust in them and vice versa.
ثقة متبادلة فيما بيننا
And I also have to build their faith.
وكان علي ان انمي إيمانه في الهدف
And that's a new kind of leadership
وهذه هي القيادة
for me.
بالنسبة لي ( ثقة - إيمان )
We had one operation
كانت احدى العمليات التي لدي
where we had to coordinate it from multiple locations.
ان انسق بين عدة مواقع سوية
An emerging opportunity came --
كانت فرصة نادرة
didn't have time to get everybody together.
ولم يكن لدي الوقت لكي اجتمع مع كل القادة
So we had to get complex intelligence together,
فقمنا بالذهاب الى مركز المعلومات الرقمية .. وعقدنا مؤتمر مرئي
we had to line up the ability to act.
وكان لدينا جميعاً القدرة على التواصل
It was sensitive, we had to go up the chain of command,
كان الامر حساساً .. كان هناك تسلسل قيادي كبير لكي نصل
convince them that this was the right thing to do
الى القيام بالامر على هذا النحو
and do all of this
اي ان نقود العملية
on electronic medium.
بواسطة اجتماع مرئي رقمي
We failed.
لقد فشلنا حينها ..
The mission didn't work.
لم تنجح المهمة
And so now what we had to do
وكان يجب حينها علي كقائد ..
is I had to reach out
اتواصل مع الجميع
to try to rebuild the trust of that force,
واحاول اعادة بناء الثقة
rebuild their confidence --
من جديد
me and them, and them and me,
سواء كنت اقصد ثقتي او ثقتهم
and our seniors and us as a force --
وكنت ومع القادة من حولي
all without the ability to put a hand on a shoulder.
غير قادرين على التواصل المباشر ( التربيت على الكتف )
Entirely new requirement.
انه عصر جديد .. يتطلب متطلبات جديدة ..
Also, the people had changed.
ناهيكم على ان الجنود تغيروا ..
You probably think that the force that I led
ربما تظنوا ان من اقودهم ..
was all steely-eyed commandos with big knuckle fists
هم حادوا النظر .. هائبوا المنظر ..
carrying exotic weapons.
يحملون الاسلحة الثقيلة
In reality,
في الحقيقة ..
much of the force I led
معظم الجنود الذين اقودهم ..
looked exactly like you.
يبدون مثلكم تماما ..
It was men, women, young, old --
انهم .. رجال .. نساء ..شبان .. شابات
not just from military; from different organizations,
ليسوا فحسب من الجيش .. بل من منظمات عدة
many of them detailed to us just from a handshake.
العديد منهم تحت امرتنا .. جراء مصافحة فحسب
And so instead of giving orders,
وبدلاً من اعطاء الاوامر
you're now building consensus
انت الان تبني " توافق آراء "
and you're building a sense of shared purpose.
وانت تبني " هدف مشترك "
Probably the biggest change
وربما التغير الاكبر
was understanding that the generational difference,
هو اننا نستوعب اننا مختلفون عن بعضنا البعض
the ages, had changed so much.
في الاعمار .. والتقنيات .. وهذا يغير الكثير
I went down to be with a Ranger platoon
لقد ذهبت مع احدى الفصائل
on an operation in Afghanistan,
في عملية في أفغانستان
and on that operation,
وفي تلك العملية
a sergeant in the platoon
كان الضابط في تلك الفصيلة
had lost about half his arm
قد فقد ذراعه
throwing a Taliban hand grenade
اثناء اعادة رمي قنبلة كانت "طالبان" قد رمتها علينا
back at the enemy
كان يريد ان يرميها مجددا اليهم
after it had landed in his fire team.
وبعد انتهاء العملية
We talked about the operation,
جلسنا نتحدث عنها
and then at the end I did what I often do with a force like that.
كما افعل عادة بعد اي عملية قتالية
I asked, "Where were you on 9/11?"
ومن ثم سئلت الجميع " اين كنتم في 11/9 "
And one young Ranger in the back --
فخرج احد المجندين من الخلف
his hair's tousled and his face is red and windblown
كان شعره اشعث وكان وجه قد شابه الاحمرار
from being in combat in the cold Afghan wind --
بسبب الرياح الباردة في افغانستان
he said, "Sir, I was in the sixth grade."
وقال " سيدي .. لقد كنت في الطابق السادس "
And it reminded me
وهذا ذكرني
that we're operating a force
اننا قوى عسكرية
that must have shared purpose
ونحتاج الى هدف مشترك
and shared consciousness,
ووعي مشترك
and yet he has different experiences,
ورغم هذا .. كانت تجربته مختلفة
in many cases a different vocabulary,
في عدة اوجه .. صاغ الامر بكلمات جديدة ..
a completely different skill set
بمهارات جديدة ..
in terms of digital media
من خلال مبدأ " الرقمية الحديثة "
than I do and many of the other senior leaders.
ومن ثم قمت بقيادة عدة معارك جدية ..
And yet, we need to have that shared sense.
ولكن كل ما كنا نحتاجه .. هو الشعور المشترك ..
It also produced something
وهذا يولد
which I call an inversion of expertise,
ما اسميه " انعكاس خبرة "
because we had so many changes at the lower levels
لقد تغير الكثير على المستوى الاساسي
in technology and tactics and whatnot,
ان التكنولوجيا والتكتيكات ..
that suddenly the things that we grew up doing
فجأة بدات تتحكم بكل شيء
wasn't what the force was doing anymore.
وما تدربنا عليه لم يعد يستخدم
So how does a leader
والسؤال الاهم هو .. كيف يمكن للقائد
stay credible and legitimate
ان يملك المصداقية ..و الشرعية
when they haven't done
عندما يقود افراد .. يستخدمون ويقومون
what the people you're leading are doing?
بأشياء هو نفسه لم يقم بها ؟
And it's a brand new leadership challenge.
انه تحد جديد للقيادة ..
And it forced me to become a lot more transparent,
وهذا دفعني لان اصبح من انصار الشفافية اكثر
a lot more willing to listen,
وان اميل للاستماع اكثر
a lot more willing to be reverse-mentored from lower.
وان استمع اكثر الى المستوى الادنى من القوات
And yet, again, you're not all in one room.
ومرة اخرى .. انهم ليسوا في غرفة واحدة
Then another thing.
وهنا شيء آخر
There's an effect on you and on your leaders.
هناك تأثير عليك .. وعلى قادتك ..
There's an impact, it's cumulative.
هناك تأثير .. انه تراكمي ..
You don't reset, or recharge your battery every time.
لايمكن التراجع عن تأثيره .. انه ليس شيء يستهلك ويعاد شحنه ( الدعم النفسي )
I stood in front of a screen one night in Iraq
كنت اقف ذات يوم امام شاشة في العراق
with one of my senior officers
مع احد كبار الضباط
and we watched a firefight from one of our forces.
وكنا نشاهد معركة تجري بين قواتنا والعدو
And I remembered his son was in our force.
واتذكر ان ابن الضابط كان في تلك المعركة
And I said, "John, where's your son? And how is he?"
فسئلته " جون .. اين هو ابنك .. اين هو "
And he said, "Sir, he's fine. Thanks for asking."
فقال لي " انه بخير .. شكرا لك سيدي "
I said, "Where is he now?"
سئلت . " اين هو الان "
And he pointed at the screen, he said, "He's in that firefight."
فأشار الى الشاشة .. وقال .. هذا هو .. هو في خضم المعركة
Think about watching your brother, father,
تصور ان تشاهد ابنك .. والدك
daughter, son, wife
هكذا .. في هذا الموقف
in a firefight in real time
في معركة جارية
and you can't do anything about it.
ولايمكنك ان تقوم باي شيء
Think about knowing that over time.
تصور معرفة هذا على الدوام
And it's a new cumulative pressure on leaders.
انه ضغط جديد متراكم يواكب القادة اليوم
And you have to watch and take care of each other.
وعليك ان تشاهد .. وان تهتم بالجميع
I probably learned the most about relationships.
ربما اكثر ما استفدت منه هو الخبرة في العلاقات البشرية
I learned they are the sinew
لقد ايقنت انها العصب - الملاط -
which hold the force together.
الذي يجمع كل القوات سوية
I grew up much of my career in the Ranger regiment.
لقد قضيت معظم مسيرتي بسرية الحماية
And every morning in the Ranger regiment,
كنت كل صباح في تلك السرية
every Ranger -- and there are more than 2,000 of them --
كل جندي .. كنا ما يقارب 2000 جندي
says a six-stanza Ranger creed.
نقول ستة مقاطع من مقاطع السرية
You may know one line of it, it says,
ربما تعلمون واحد منها .. انها تنص على ..
"I'll never leave a fallen comrade to fall into the hands of the enemy."
" لن اسمح بوقوع رفيق في يد العدو "
And it's not a mindless mantra,
وهي ليست تعويذة ..
and it's not a poem.
وليست شعراً او نثراً
It's a promise.
انه وعد
Every Ranger promises every other Ranger,
كل مجند يتعهد للمجند الآخر
"No matter what happens, no matter what it costs me,
انه مهما حدث .. ومهما سيكلف الامر
if you need me, I'm coming."
ان احتجت لي .. فسوف أتي
And every Ranger gets that same promise
وكل مجند يعده احدهم بهذا
from every other Ranger.
من رفاقه المجندين
Think about it. It's extraordinarily powerful.
فكروا .. بهذا .. انه عهد قوي حقاً
It's probably more powerful than marriage vows.
انه اقوى من عهود الزواج
And they've lived up to it, which gives it special power.
وهم يعيشون عليه .. انه يعطي قوة خاصة
And so the organizational relationship that bonds them
وهو يرتب العلاقات فيما بينهم .. ويقويها
is just amazing.
انه امرٌ رائع
And I learned personal relationships
وتعلمت ان العلاقات الشخصية
were more important than ever.
هي اهم ما على الوجود
We were in a difficult operation in Afghanistan in 2007,
كنا في عملية صعبة في افغانستان في عام 2007
and an old friend of mine,
وصديق قديم لي
that I had spent many years
كنت قد قضيت مدة طويلة
at various points of my career with --
من حياتي المهنية معه
godfather to one of their kids --
انا عراب احد اطفاله
he sent me a note, just in an envelope,
ارسل الي رسالة .. في الحقيقة ظرف
that had a quote from Sherman to Grant
فيه اقتباس من رسائل " شيرمان الى جرانت "
that said, "I knew if I ever got in a tight spot,
تقول " انا متأكد انه ان كان هناك اي منفذ لمساعدتي مهما كان ضيقاً
that you would come, if alive."
فسوف تأتي منه انت .. ان كنت على قيد الحياة "
And having that kind of relationship, for me,
وان تملك هذا النوع من العلاقات بالنسبة لي
turned out to be critical at many points in my career.
كان محوريا في مسيرتي المهنة .. بل هي التي صنعتها
And I learned that you have to give that
وتعلمت انه يتوجب على الفرد ان يعطي هذا التميز لمن حوله
in this environment,
خاصة في بيئة
because it's tough.
قاسية مثل بيئة الجيش
That was my journey.
هذه هي مسيرتي
I hope it's not over.
اتمنى ان لا تنتهي قريباً
I came to believe
وانا اليوم أؤمن
that a leader isn't good because they're right;
ان القائد الجيد ليس هو كذلك لانه مصيب
they're good because they're willing to learn and to trust.
ولكنه هو كذلك لانه مستعد للتعلم .. والثقة
This isn't easy stuff.
وهذه ليست امور سهلة
It's not like that electronic abs machine
انها ليست كمثل آلة تدريب عضلات المعدة
where, 15 minutes a month, you get washboard abs.
حيث يمكنك ان تاخذ تمارين لمدة 15 دقيقة فتحصل على عضلات معدة مميزة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And it isn't always fair.
والامر ليس سلساً وليس عادلاً
You can get knocked down,
يمكن ان تهزم
and it hurts
ويمكن ان تصاب
and it leaves scars.
ويمكن ان تصاب بالندوب
But if you're a leader,
ولكن ان كنت قائداً
the people you've counted on
فان الاشخاص الذين تعتمد عليهم
will help you up.
سوف يساعدوك لامحالة
And if you're a leader,
وان كنت قائداً
the people who count on you need you on your feet.
فان الاشخاص الذين تعتمد عليهم .. سوف يساعدوك لكي تقف من جديد على قدميك
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)